1.3 billion years ago,
منذ 1.3 مليار عاماً
in a distant, distant galaxy,
في مجرة بعيدة جداً
two black holes locked into a spiral,
إثنان من الثقوب السوداء قد حُبسوا في دوامة
falling inexorably towards each other
ساقطين بلا هوادة كل منهم فى اتجاه الآخر
and collided,
و اصطدما
converting three Suns' worth of stuff
محولة بقيمة تعادل ثلاثة شموس
into pure energy in a tenth of a second.
إلى طاقة نقية في عُشر من الثانية
For that brief moment in time,
من أجل هذه اللحظة الوجيزة من الوقت،
the glow was brighter than all the stars
كان الوهج أكثر إشراقاً من كل النجوم
in all the galaxies
في كل المجرات
in all of the known Universe.
في كل الكون المعروف
It was a very
لقد كان انفجار
big
عظيم
bang.
جداً
But they didn't release their energy in light.
و لكنهم لم يظهروا طاقتهم في الضوء
I mean, you know, they're black holes.
أنا أقصد - أنتم تعرفون - أنها ثقوب سوداء
All that energy was pumped into the fabric of space and time itself,
كل هذه الطاقة قد تم ضخها في شبكة المكان والزمان نفسها،
making the Universe explode in gravitational waves.
مما جعل الكون ينفجر في موجات الجاذبية
Let me give you a sense of the timescale at work here.
اسمحوا لي أن أعطيكم معنى المقياس الزمني في العمل هنا
1.3 billion years ago,
منذ 1.3 مليار عاماً
Earth had just managed to evolve multicellular life.
تمكنت الأرض أن تطور الحياة متعددة الخلايا
Since then, Earth has made and evolved
منذ ذلك الحين، تكونت الأرض و تطورت
corals, fish, plants, dinosaurs, people and even -- God save us -- the Internet.
الشعاب المرجانية والأسماك والديناصورات والنباتات والناس وحتى-الله يحفظنا-الأنترنت
And about 25 years ago,
و منذ حوالي 25 عاماً
a particularly audacious set of people --
بشكل خاص مجموعة من الشجعان
Rai Weiss at MIT, Kip Thorne and Ronald Drever at Caltech --
راي ويس في ماساتشوستس و كيب ثورن و رونالد دريفر في كالتيك
decided that it would be really neat
قرروا أنه سيكون حقاً رائع
to build a giant laser detector
لبناء كاشف ليزر عملاق
with which to search for the gravitational waves
نستخدمه للبحث عن موجات الجاذبية
from things like colliding black holes.
من أشياء مثل اصطدام الثقوب السوداء
Now, most people thought they were nuts.
الآن، معظم الناس اعتقدوا أنهم مجانين
But enough people realized that they were brilliant nuts
لكن عدد كافٍ من الناس أدرك أنهم عباقرة مجانين
that the US National Science Foundation decided to fund their crazy idea.
أن المؤسسة الوطنية الأمريكية للعلوم قررت أن تمول فكرتهم المجنونة
So after decades of development,
لذلك بعد عقود من التطور
construction and imagination
البناء و التخيل
and a breathtaking amount of hard work,
و كمية لإلتقاط النفس من العمل الجاد
they built their detector, called LIGO:
بنوا كاشفهم، يدعى LIGO
The Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory.
الليزر المرصد لتداخل موجات الجاذبية
For the last several years,
على مدى السنوات الأخيرة
LIGO's been undergoing a huge expansion in its accuracy,
LIGO شهد توسع كبير في دقته
a tremendous improvement in its detection ability.
تحسينات ضخمة في قدرته على الكشف
It's now called Advanced LIGO as a result.
إنه يدعى الآن LIGO المتطور كنتيجة لذلك
In early September of 2015,
في أوائل سبتمبر عام 2015
LIGO turned on for a final test run
LIGO أدير من أجل الاختبار النهائي
while they sorted out a few lingering details.
في حين قاموا بشرح بعض التفاصيل الثابتة
And on September 14 of 2015,
و في 14 سبتمبر عام 2015
just days after the detector had gone live,
بعد أيام من عمل الكاشف
the gravitational waves from those colliding black holes
موجات الجاذبية من هذه الثقوب السوداء المتصادمة
passed through the Earth.
انتقلت إلى الأرض
And they passed through you and me.
و انتقلت من خلالي و من خلالك
And they passed through the detector.
و انتقلت من خلال الكاشف
(Audio) Scott Hughes: There's two moments in my life
(صوت) سكوت هغز: يوجد لحظتان في حياتى
more emotionally intense than that.
أكثر شدة عاطفياً من ذلك
One is the birth of my daughter.
واحدة هي ميلاد ابنتى
The other is when I had to say goodbye to my father when he was terminally ill.
الأخرى هي عندما كان يجب علي أن أقول الوداع لأبي عندما كان مريض ميؤوس من شفائه
You know, it was the payoff of my career, basically.
أنتم تعلمون، أنها كانت مكافأة مشوارى المهني، في الأساس
Everything I'd been working on -- it's no longer science fiction! (Laughs)
كل الأشياء التي كنت أعمل عليها لم تعد خيال علمي (ضحك)
Allan Adams: So that's my very good friend and collaborator, Scott Hughes,
الآن أدامز: هذا صديقي الجيد و المتعاون سكوت هغز
a theoretical physicist at MIT,
عالم الفيزياء النظرية فى MIT
who has been studying gravitational waves from black holes
الذي كان يدرس موجات الجاذبية من الثقوب السوداء
and the signals that they could impart on observatories like LIGO,
و الإشارات التي تستطيع نقل المراصد مثل LIGO
for the past 23 years.
على مدى السنوات ال 23 الماضية.
So let me take a moment to tell you what I mean by a gravitational wave.
لذلك دعونى أتوقف لحظة لأقول لكم ما أعنيه بموجة الجاذبية
A gravitational wave is a ripple
موجة الجاذبية هي موجة
in the shape of space and time.
في شكل المكان و الزمان
As the wave passes by,
بمجرد مرور الموجة
it stretches space and everything in it
تمد المكان و كل شيء فيها
in one direction,
في اتجاه واحد
and compresses it in the other.
و تضغظها في الإتجاه الأخر
This has led to countless instructors of general relativity
وقد أدى ذلك إلى عدد لا يحصى من المدربين في النسبية العامة
doing a really silly dance to demonstrate in their classes on general relativity.
يقومون برقص سخيف جداً لوصف النسبية العامة في فصولهم
"It stretches and expands, it stretches and expands."
" انها تتمدد و تتسع، انها تتمدد و تتسع"
So the trouble with gravitational waves
لذلك المشكلة بموجات الجاذبية
is that they're very weak; they're preposterously weak.
أنها ضعيفة جداً، إنها ضعيفة بطريقة غير معقولة
For example, the waves that hit us on September 14 --
فمثلاً، الموجات التي صدمتنا في 14 سبتمبر
and yes, every single one of you stretched and compressed
و نعم، كل واحد منكم تمدد و انضعط
under the action of that wave --
تحت تأثير هذه الموجة
when the waves hit, they stretched the average person
عندما تصدم الموجات، يمدوا الشخص العادي
by one part in 10 to the 21.
إلى جزء واحد من 10 إلى 21
That's a decimal place, 20 zeroes,
هذا هو المكان العشري ، 20 صفر
and a one.
و واحد
That's why everyone thought the LIGO people were nuts.
لهذا السبب كل شخص اعتقد أن LIGO كانوا مجانين
Even with a laser detector five kilometers long -- and that's already crazy --
حتى بكاشف ليزر 5 كيلومتر طولاً -- و هذا بالفعل جنون--
they would have to measure the length of those detectors
كان يجب عليهم أن يقيسوا طول هذه الكواشف
to less than one thousandth of the radius of the nucleus
إلى أقل من 1 جزء من الألف من نصف قطر النواة
of an atom.
من الذرة
And that's preposterous.
و هذا غير معقول
So towards the end of his classic text on gravity,
لذلك في اتجاه نهاية النص الكلاسيكي عن الجاذبية
LIGO co-founder Kip Thorne
كيب ثورن المؤسس المشارك ب LIGO
described the hunt for gravitational waves as follows:
وصف البحث عن موجات الجاذبية على النحو التالي
He said, "The technical difficulties to be surmounted
قال" الصعوبات التقنية التي يجب التغلب عليها
in constructing such detectors
في بناء هذه الكاشفات
are enormous.
ضخمة
But physicists are ingenious,
و لكن الفيزيائين مبتكرين
and with the support of a broad lay public,
و مع الدعم من جمهور العامة
all obstacles will surely be overcome."
كل العقبات سوف يتم التغلب عليها بالتأكيد
Thorne published that in 1973,
نشر ثورن ذلك في 1973
42 years before he succeeded.
42 عاماً قبل أن ينجح
Now, coming back to LIGO,
الآن، نعود إلى LIGO
Scott likes to say that LIGO acts like an ear
سكوت يحب أن يقول أن LIGO تتصرف كأذن
more than it does like an eye.
أكثر مما تفعل كعين
I want to explain what that means.
أريد أن أشرح ماذا يعني ذلك
Visible light has a wavelength, a size,
الضوء المرئى لديه طول موجي - حجم -
that's much smaller than the things around you,
الذي يكون أصغر بكثير من الأشياء التي حولك.
the features on people's faces,
الملامح على وجوه الناس
the size of your cell phone.
حجم هاتفك المحمول
And that's really useful,
و هذا مفيد جداً
because it lets you make an image or a map of the things around you,
لأنه يجعلك تصنع صورة أو خريطة للأشياء التي حولك.
by looking at the light coming from different spots
عن طريق النظر إلى الضوء الذى يأتي من الأماكن المختلفة
in the scene about you.
في المشهد الذي حولك.
Sound is different.
الصوت مختلف
Audible sound has a wavelength that can be up to 50 feet long.
الصوت المسموع له طول موجي يمكنه أن يصل إلى 50 قدم في الطول
And that makes it really difficult --
و هذا يجعله حقاً صعب
in fact, in practical purposes, impossible -- to make an image
في الحقيقة - في الأغراض العملية- مستحيل عمل صورة
of something you really care about.
شئ أنت حقاً تهتم به
Your child's face.
صورة طفلك
Instead, we use sound to listen for features like pitch
بدلاً من ذلك، نستخدم الصوت لنسمع خصائص كالاهتزازة
and tone and rhythm and volume
و النغمة و الإيقاع و الصوت.
to infer a story behind the sounds.
لتخمين قصة خلف الأصوات.
That's Alice talking.
هذا أليس يتحدث
That's Bob interrupting.
هذا بوب يقاطع
Silly Bob.
بوب السخيف
So, the same is true of gravitational waves.
لذلك نفس الشيء هو حقيقة موجات الجاذبية
We can't use them to make simple images of things out in the Universe.
لا نستطيع أن نستخدمهم لنصنع صور بسيطة لأشياء في الكون
But by listening to changes
و لكن بالإستماع إلى التغيرات
in the amplitude and frequency of those waves,
في السعة و التردد لهذه الموجات
we can hear the story that those waves are telling.
نستطيع أن نسمع القصة أن هذه الموجات تخبرنا.
And at least for LIGO,
و على الأقل، بالنسبة ل LIGO ،
the frequencies that it can hear are in the audio band.
الترددات التي من الممكن سمعها موجودة في النطاق الصوتي
So if we convert the wave patterns into pressure waves and air, into sound,
لذلك إذا حولنا أنماط الموجة إلى موجات ضغط و هواء إلى صوت
we can literally hear the Universe speaking to us.
نستطيع حرفياً أن نسمع الكون يتحدث إلينا
For example, listening to gravity, just in this way,
على سبيل المثال، الإستماع إلى الجاذبية -فقط بهذه الطريقة-
can tell us a lot about the collision of two black holes,
تسطيع أن تخبرنا الكثير عن تصادم الثقبين الأسودين
something my colleague Scott has spent an awful lot of time thinking about.
شيء قضى فيه زميلى سكوت قدراً هائلاً من الوقت يفكر فيه.
(Audio) SH: If the two black holes are non-spinning,
(صوت) سكوت : لو كانا الثقبان الأسودان غير دائرين حول أنفسهم
you get a very simple chirp: whoop!
تحصل على تغريد بسيط جداً. هووب !
If the two bodies are spinning very rapidly, I have that same chirp,
لو الجسمان يدوران بسرعة جداً، سوف أحصل على نفس التغريد
but with a modulation on top of it,
و لكن بتعديل في أعلاها
so it kind of goes: whir, whir, whir!
لذلك إنها نوعاً ما تعمل: وير، وير، وير!
It's sort of the vocabulary of spin imprinted on this waveform.
إنها بشكل ما مصطلحات الدوران مطبوعة على شكل الموجة
AA: So on September 14, 2015,
أدامز : لذلك في 14 سبتمبر 2015
a date that's definitely going to live in my memory,
تاريخ بلا شك سوف يعيش في ذاكرتي
LIGO heard this:
سمعت LIGO ذلك
[Whirring sound]
( صوت موجات)
So if you know how to listen, that is the sound of --
لذلك إذا كنت تعرف كيف تسمع، هذا صوت --
(Audio) SH: ... two black holes, each of about 30 solar masses,
( صوت) سكوت : ... ثقبان أسودان -كل منهم في حوالى كتلة 30 شمساً-
that were whirling around at a rate
كانا يدوران بمعدل
comparable to what goes on in your blender.
مشابه إلى ما يحدث في خلاطك.
AA: It's worth pausing here to think about what that means.
أدامز : إنه يستحق أن نتوقف هنا لنفكر ماذا يعني هذا
Two black holes, the densest thing in the Universe,
ثقبان أسودان - الأكثر كثافة في الكون-
one with a mass of 29 Suns
واحد بكتلة 29 شمساً.
and one with a mass of 36 Suns,
و الأخر بكتله 36 شمساً.
whirling around each other 100 times per second
يدوران حول بعضهم البعض 100 مرة في الثانية الواحدة
before they collide.
قبل التصادم.
Just imagine the power of that.
فقط فكر في قوة ذلك.
It's fantastic.
إنه رائع
And we know it because we heard it.
و نحن نعرف هذا لأننا سمعنا ذلك
That's the lasting importance of LIGO.
هذه هي الأهمية الدائمة ل LIGO
It's an entirely new way to observe the Universe
إنها طريقة جديدة تماماً لرصد الكون
that we've never had before.
التي لم نملكها من قبل.
It's a way that lets us hear the Universe
إنها الطريقة التي تجعلنا نسمع الكون
and hear the invisible.
و نسمع الغير مرئي
And there's a lot out there that we can't see --
و يوجد الكثير حول ذلك لا نستطيع أن نراه --
in practice or even in principle.
في الممارسة أو حتى في المبدأ
So supernova, for example:
لذلك ال supernova على سبيل المثال:
I would love to know why very massive stars explode in supernovae.
أحب أن أعرف لماذا تنفجر النجوم الهائلة في ال supernovae.
They're very useful;
إنها مفيدة جداً،
we've learned a lot about the Universe from them.
لقد عرفنا الكثير عن الكون منهم.
The problem is, all the interesting physics happens in the core,
المشكلة هي كل الفيزياء المثيرة تحدث في النواة
and the core is hidden behind thousands of kilometers
و النواه مختبأة حول آلاف الكيلومترات.
of iron and carbon and silicon.
من الحديد و الكربون و السيلكون
We'll never see through it, it's opaque to light.
لن نستطيع أن نرى من خلالها ، أنها معتمة للضوء
Gravitational waves go through iron as if it were glass --
موجات الجاذبية تذهب خلال الحديد كما لو كانت زجاج
totally transparent.
شفافة تماماً
The Big Bang: I would love to be able to explore
الإنفجار العظيم: أحب أن أكون قادراً أن أستكشف
the first few moments of the Universe,
اللحظات القليلة الأولى من الكون
but we'll never see them,
و لكننا لن نراها
because the Big Bang itself is obscured by its own afterglow.
لأن الإنفجار العظيم نفسه يُحجب بواسطة الشفق
With gravitational waves,
عن طريق موجات الجاذبية
we should be able to see all the way back to the beginning.
ينبغي أن نكون قادرين على رؤية كل الطريق منذ البداية
Perhaps most importantly,
ربما الأكثر أهمية،
I'm positive that there are things out there
أنا متفائل أنه يوجد أشياء هناك
that we've never seen
لم نستطيع أن نراها
that we may never be able to see
و أنه من الممكن ألا نراها
and that we haven't even imagined --
و لم نتخيلها أبداً
things that we'll only discover by listening.
أشياء سوف نكتشفها فقط بالإستماع
And in fact, even in that very first event,
و في الحقيقة، حتى في أول الحدث
LIGO found things that we didn't expect.
LIGO وجدت أشياء لم نتوقعها
Here's my colleague and one of the key members of the LIGO collaboration,
هذا زميلي وواحد من الأعضاء الرئيسين في LIGO
Matt Evans, my colleague at MIT, addressing exactly that:
مات إيفانز زميلي فى MIT متناولاً بالضبط ذلك:
(Audio) Matt Evans: The kinds of stars which produce the black holes
(صوت) مات إيفانز: أنواع النجوم التي تنتج الثقوب السوداء
that we observed here
التي رصدناها
are the dinosaurs of the Universe.
هم ديناصورات الكون
They're these massive things that are old, from prehistoric times,
إنهم تلك الأشياء الهائلة التي تكون قديمة من أوقات ما قبل التاريخ
and the black holes are kind of like the dinosaur bones
و الثقوب السوداء هي نوع مثل عظام الديناصورات
with which we do this archeology.
و التي بها نقوم بعلم الأثار
So it lets us really get a whole nother angle
لذلك هي تسمح لنا حقاً بالحصول على زاوية مختلفة تماماً
on what's out there in the Universe
على ما هناك في الكون
and how the stars came to be, and in the end, of course,
و كيف تكونت النجوم و في النهاية بالتأكيد
how we came to be out of this whole mess.
كيف أصبحنا خارج كل هذه الفوضى.
AA: Our challenge now
أدامز: تحدينا الأن
is to be as audacious as possible.
أن نكون شجعان بالقدر الممكن.
Thanks to LIGO, we know how to build exquisite detectors
و الفضل يرجع إلى LIGO نحن نعرف كيف أن نبني كواشف رائعة
that can listen to the Universe,
التي تسطيع أن تسمع الكون.
to the rustle and the chirp of the cosmos.
إلى حفيف و تغريد الكون.
Our job is to dream up and build new observatories --
وظيفتنا هي أن نحلم بأفضل و نبنى رواصد
a whole new generation of observatories --
جيل جديد جداً من الرواصد
on the ground, in space.
على الأرض، في الفضاء.
I mean, what could be more glorious than listening to the Big Bang itself?
أنا أعني، ماذا يكون أعظم من الإستماع إلى الإنفجار العظيم نفسه؟
Our job now is to dream big.
وظيفتنا هي أن نحلم بعظمة.
Dream with us.
إحلم معنا
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)